<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">PRL Blog: PRL Blog</title>
 <link rel="self" href="http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" />
 <link href="http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/index.html" />
 <id>urn:http-prl-ccs-neu-edu:-blog-index-html</id>
 <updated>2016-05-03T12:21:07Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">NEPLS on May 31st at UMass, Amherst</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/blog/2016/05/03/nepls-on-may-31st-at-umass-amherst/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-prl-ccs-neu-edu:-blog-blog-2016-05-03-nepls-on-may-31st-at-umass-amherst</id>
  <published>2016-05-03T12:21:07Z</published>
  <updated>2016-05-03T12:21:07Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>PRL</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my pleasure to relay the following announcement for the next edition of the New England Programming Language Seminer (NEPLS), to be held on Tuesday May 31st at UMass, Amherst, organized by Arjun Guha. Venez nombreux!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;The next New England Programming Languages and Systems Symposium will take place on Tuesday, May 31st 2016 at University of Massachusetts, Amherst. Please mark it in your calendars!&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;The speaker selection committee solicits talks for this meeting. To propose yourself or someone else, send a title, list of authors, and a brief description. You may provide UP TO ONE PAGE of description, but you can keep it as short as a paragraph. We particularly invite talks by researchers from outside the area who are visiting on the date of the NEPLS meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;Talks can vary in length. Though 30-minute conference-style slots are traditional, speakers may request slots of as little as 5 minutes; we encourage the shorter formats. This variety permits the presentation of smaller results, preliminary work, progress reports on ongoing projects (such as language standards and compiler toolkits), and updates to past presentations. In general, NEPLS talks need not sound like conference presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;The submission deadline is Tuesday, May 17th. Send your proposal to talks@nepls.org.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;More details about NEPLS are available on the NEPLS webpage:&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt; http://www.nepls.org/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m personally fond of such regional events, which is a great time to learn about the research around us in a less formal and exhausting setting than a 200-attendees conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in the area, please consider applying to talk about your work. If one of your colleague is working on something you find exciting, please invite them to apply!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Welcome to the PRL blog</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/blog/2016/04/29/welcome-to-the-prl-blog/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-prl-ccs-neu-edu:-blog-blog-2016-04-29-welcome-to-the-prl-blog</id>
  <published>2016-04-29T18:50:29Z</published>
  <updated>2016-04-29T18:50:29Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>PRL</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greetings, ground rules, hopes, dreams, and notes for contributors. Welcome aboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, the Programming Research Lab (PRL) was blessed with a new  postdoc: &lt;a href="http://gallium.inria.fr/~scherer/"&gt;Gabriel Scherer&lt;/a&gt; from INRIA  Paris-Rocquencourt, France. Ever since Gabriel arrived things have been changing here in Boston. We now have homemade bread on the first Tuesday of every month,  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orange_flower_water"&gt;orange water&lt;/a&gt; crepes  after holidays, and someone new to go out for bubble tea with in between. All that and an enthusiastic colleague and researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his spare time between lobbying the CS department for an espresso machine and  building multi-language compilers, Gabriel is also a champion of open access. Hence this blog, a window into the life and times of PRL students made  possible by Gabriel&amp;rsquo;s tactical prodding and careful delegation of responsibilities. Anything you might read about in a rejected conference paper or hear over  coffee is fair game here: the goal is to give the wide world a glimpse of  our lab and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="for-contributors"&gt;For Contributors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These pages are generated using Greg Hendershott&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://github.com/greghendershott/frog"&gt;frog&lt;/a&gt;  static website generator. To create a new post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Clone or fork the &lt;a href="https://github.com/nuprl/nuprl.github.io"&gt;nuprl.github.io&lt;/a&gt; repository&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Check out a new git branch for your post&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;cd blog; raco frog -n "TITLE"&lt;/code&gt; to build a template for a new post&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Add content to the new markdown file (under &lt;code&gt;_src/posts&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Rebuild the blog with &lt;code&gt;raco frog -b&lt;/code&gt;, view your changes at &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Send a pull request to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/nuprl/nuprl.github.io"&gt;nuprl.github.io&lt;/a&gt; repo&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open pull request is the best place to ask questions about the formatting or content of a post. We promise that within a few days of opening a PR someone with push access will reply with feedback or merge the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions are open to anyone: current labmates, alumni, friends from the  Racket mailing list, and even recovering C programmers. One should have a strong connection to Northeastern or our research, but  even that is not strictly necessary. Visitors are always welcome to the PRL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry></feed>