<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>PRL Blog: Posts tagged 'castle'</title>
  <description>PRL Blog: Posts tagged 'castle'</description>
  <link>http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/tags/castle.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:40:16 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:40:16 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>PLISS: Learn About PL Implementation in a Castle</title>
   <link>http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/2019/03/09/pliss-learn-about-pl-implementation-in-a-castle/?utm_source=castle&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:http-prl-ccs-neu-edu:-blog-2019-03-09-pliss-learn-about-pl-implementation-in-a-castle</guid>
   <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:40:16 UT</pubDate>
   <author>PRL</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;We love programming languages (PLs), and we should all be in on the ins and outs of implementing them. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning the tricks of the trade of PL design and implementation, what better opportunity than the second Programming Languages Implementation Summer School (&lt;a href="https://pliss2019.github.io/"&gt;PLISS&lt;/a&gt; for short).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PLISS will be held from May 19th to 24th 2019, and the deadline to express your interest is &lt;em&gt;March 29th, 2019&lt;/em&gt; at &lt;em&gt;17:00 GMT&lt;/em&gt;. More details can be found &lt;a href="https://pliss2019.github.io/registration.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/img/pliss_summer_school_2017_logo.png" alt="PLISS logo" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The school will feature &lt;a href="https://pliss2019.github.io/speakers.html"&gt;ten speakers&lt;/a&gt; from both academia and industry, each well-versed in the practical side of programming languages. The lectures cover current research as well as future trends in programming language design and implementation, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Developing Security-Aware Languages with Cristina Cifuentes;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Semantics-First Language Design with Sylvan Clebsch;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Compiler Design Patterns for Machine Learning by Albert Cohen;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Design and Analysis of Configuration Languages by Arjun Guha;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A Survey of V8 and WebAssembly by Ben L. Titzer;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Crafting User-Friendly Compilers by Nicholas Matsakis;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Static Program Analysis by Anders Møller;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;How Industry Approaches Language and Compiler Design by Joe Pamer;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;What an End to Non-Volatile RAM Means for Researchers by Mario Wolczko.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides attending lectures, students will also be able to get to know the speakers and attendees and think of new research problems. A week-long stay in beautiful Bertinoro, Italy is an ideal setting for socializing with other PL enthusiasts and building lasting relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I may, I attended the first PLISS in 2017 and can&amp;rsquo;t recommend it enough. The atmosphere at summer schools is truly unparalleled, and I made friends there that have stood the test of time. For what it&amp;rsquo;s worth to any prospective graduate students, PLISS is also where I met my PhD advisor. Students will be surprised at how many faces they recognize at future conferences, and in a sense summer schools are nice introduction to the research community. You can read another attendee&amp;rsquo;s testimonial &lt;a href="http://prl.ccs.neu.edu/blog/2017/06/05/report-pliss-2017/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information can be found at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pliss2019.github.io"&gt;https://pliss2019.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(No, really, it&amp;rsquo;s in a castle. Look at the pictures.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>